part 1 chapter 5.
in the low ceiling canteen, deep underground the lunch queue jerked slowly forward.
The room was already very full and deafeningly noisy. From the Grill at the
counter the steam of stew came pouring forth, with a sour metallic smell which
did not quite overcome the fumes of Victory Gin.
On the far side of the room there was a
small bar, a mere hole in the wall, where gin could be bought at 10 cents the
large nip.
'Just the man I was looking for,' said a voice at Winston's back.
He turned round. It was his friend Sim who worked in the Research Department.
Perhaps 'friend' was not exactly the right word. You did not have friends nowadays,
you had comrades: but there were some comrades whose society was pleasanter than that of others
Simon was a philologist, a specialist in Newspeak.
Indeed, he was one of the enormous team of experts now engaged in compiling the
11th Edition of the Newspeak Dictionary.
He was a tiny creature, smaller than Winston, with dark hair and large,
protuberant eyes, at once mournful and derisive, which seemed to search your
face closely while he was speaking to you.
'I wanted to ask you whether you'd got any razor blades,' he said.
'Not one!' said Winston with a sort of guilty haste. 'I've tried all over the
place. They don't exist any longer.'
Everyone kept asking you for razor blades. Actually he had two unused ones
which he was hoarding up.
There had been a famine of them for months past.
At any given moment there was some necessary article which the Party shops
were unable to supply.
Sometimes it was buttons, sometimes it was darning wool, sometimes it was
shoelaces; at present it was razor blades.
You could only get hold of them, if at all, by scrounging more or less furtively
on the 'free' market.
'I've been using the same blade for six weeks,' he added untruthfully.
The queue gave another jerk forward.
As they halted he turned and faced Sim again.
Each of them took a greasy metal tray from a pile at the end of the counter.
'Did you go and see the prisoners hanged yesterday?' said Sim
I was working,' said Winston indifferently.
'I shall see it on the flicks, I suppose.'
'A very inadequate substitute,' said Sim His mocking eyes roved over Winston's face.
'I know you,' the eyes seem to say, 'I see through you.
I know very well why you didn't go to see those prisoners hanged.'
In an intellectual way Simon was venomously orthodox.
He would talk with a disagreeable gloating satisfaction of helicopter
raids on enemy villages and trials and confessions of thought criminals the
executions and the sellers of the Ministry of Love.
Talking to him was largely a matter of getting him away from such subjects and
entangling him, if possible, in the technicalities of Newspeak, on which he
was authoritative and interesting.
Winston turned his head a little aside to avoid the scrutiny of the large dark eyes.
'It was a good hanging,' said same reminiscently. 'I think it spoils it when
they tie their feet together.
I like to see them kicking. And above all, at the end, the tongue sticking right out,
and blue quite a bright blue. That's the detail that appeals to me
next please yield the white apron with the ladle.
Winston and Sim pushed their trays beneath the grill Onto each was dumped
swiftly the regulation lunch— —a metal panicking of pinkish gray stew, a hunk of
bread, a cube of cheese, a mug of milkless Victory Coffee, and one saccharin tablet.
'There's a table over there, under that telescreen,' said sign Let's pick up a gin on the way.'
The gin was served out to them in handle this china mugs. They threaded their way
across the crowded room and unpacked their trays onto the metal topped table,
on one corner of which someone had left a pool of stew, a filthy liquid mess that
had the appearance of vomit.
Winston took up his mug of gin, paused for an instant to collect his nerve, and
gulped the oily tasting stuff down.
When he had winked the tears out of his eyes he suddenly discovered that he was hungry.
He began swallowing spoonfuls of the stew, which, in among its general
sloppiness, had cubes of spongy pinkish stuff which was probably a preparation of meat.
Neither of them spoke again till they had emptied their pannicans
From the table at Winston's left, a little behind his back, someone was
talking rapidly and continuously, a harsh gavel almost like the quacking of a duck,
which pierced the general uproar of the room.
'How is the Dictionary getting on?' said Winston, raising his voice to overcome the noise.
'Slowly,' said Sim I'm on the adjectives.
It's fascinating.'
He had brightened up immediately at the mention of Newspeak. He pushed his
pannikin aside, took up his hunk of bread in one delicate hand and his cheese in
the other, and leaned across the table so as to be able to speak without shouting.
'The 11th Edition is the definitive edition,' he said. 'We're getting the
language into its final shape— —the shape it's going to have when nobody speaks anything else.
When we finished with it, people like you will have to learn it all over again.
You think I'd dare say, that our chief job is inventing new words. But not a bit
of it! We're destroying words— —scores of them, hundreds of them, every day.
We're cutting the language down to the bone. The 11th Edition won't contain a
single word that will become obsolete before the year 2050.'.
He bit hungrily into his bread and swallowed a couple of mouthfuls, then
continued speaking, with a sort of patent's passion.
His thin dark face had become animated, his eyes had lost their mocking
expression and grown almost dreamy.
'It's a beautiful thing, the destruction of words. Of course the great wastage is
in the verbs and adjectives, but there are hundreds of nouns that can be got
rid of as well.
It isn't only the synonyms; there are also the antonyms. After all, what
justification is there for a word which is simply the opposite of some other word?
A word contains its opposite in itself.
Take "good", for instance. If you have a word like "good", what need is there for a
word like "bad"?
"Ungood" will do just as well— —better, because it's an exact opposite, which the other is not.
Or again, if you want a stronger version of "good", what sense is there in having a
whole string of vague useless words like "excellent" and "splendid" and all the rest of them
pluscode covers the meaning; or double plus good if you want something stronger still.
Of course we use those forms already, but in the final version of Newspeak
there'll be nothing else.
In the end the whole notion of goodness and badness will be covered by only six
words— —in reality, only one word. Don't you see the beauty of that, Winston? It was
BB's idea originally, of course,' he added it as an afterthought.
A sort of vapodeagonist flitted across Winston's face at the mention of Big Brother.
Nevertheless I'm immediately detected a certain lack of enthusiasm.
'You haven't a real appreciation of new speak Winston,' he said almost sadly. 'Even
when you write it you're still thinking in Old speak I've read some of those pieces that you
write in the Times occasionally. They're good enough, but they're translations.
In your heart you'd prefer to stick to Old speak with all its vagueness and its
useless shades of meaning.
You don't grasp the beauty of the destruction of words.
Do you know that Newspeak is the only language in the world whose vocabulary
gets smaller every year?'
Winston did know that, of course. He smiled, sympathetically he hoped, not
trusting himself to speak sign bit off another fragment of the
dark colored bread Jude it briefly, and went on: 'Don't you see that the whole aim of news
speakers to narrow the range of thought?
In the end we shall make thought crime literally impossible, because there will
be no words in which to express it.
Every concept that can ever be needed will be expressed by exactly one word,
with its meaning rigidly defined and all its subsidiary meanings rubbed out and forgotten.
Already, in the 11th Edition, we're not far from that point.
But the process will still be continuing long after you and I are dead.
Every year fewer and fewer words, and the range of consciousness always a little smaller.
Even now, of course, there's no reason or excuse for committing thought crime It's
merely a question of self-discipline reality control But in the end there won't be any need
even for that.
The Revolution will be complete when the language is perfect news speak isingsoc
and ing sock is Newspeak,' he added with a sort of mystical satisfaction. Has it
ever occurred to you, Winston, that by the year 2050, at the very latest, not a
single human being will be alive who could understand such a conversation as we are having now?'
'Except———' began Winston doubtfully, and he stopped.
It had been on the tip of his tongue to say 'Except the proles,' but he checked
himself, not feeling fully certain that this remark was not in some way unorthodox
same however, had defined what he was about to say.
'The proles are not human beings,' he said carelessly. 'By 2050— —earlier, probably— —all
real knowledge of old speak will have disappeared. The whole literature of the
past will have been destroyed. Chaucer, Shakespeare, Milton, Byron— —they'll exist
only in Newspeak versions, not merely changed into something different, but
actually changed into something contradictory of what they used to be.
Even the literature of the Party will change.
Even the slogans will change. How could you have a slogan like "freedom is
slavery" when the concept of freedom has been abolished?
The whole climate of thought will be different.
In fact there will be no thought, as we understand it now.
Orthodoxy means not thinking— —not needing to think. Orthodoxy is unconsciousness.'
One of these days, thought Winston with sudden deep conviction Sam will be
vaporized. He is too intelligent. He sees too clearly and speaks too plainly.
The Party does not like such people. One day he will disappear. It is written in his face.
Winston had finished his bread and cheese. He turned a little sideways in
his chair to drink his mug of coffee.
At the table on his left the man with a strident voice was still talking remorselessly away.
A young woman who was perhaps his secretary, and who was sitting with her
back to Winston, was listening to him and seemed to be eagerly agreeing with
everything that he said.
From time to time Winston caught some such remarkers I think you're so right. I
do so agree with you', uttered in a youthful and rather silly feminine voice.
But the other voice never stopped for an instant, even when the girl was speaking.
Winston knew the man by sight, though he knew no more about him than that he held
some important post in the Fiction Department.
He was a man of about 30 with a muscular throat and a large, mobile mouth.
His head was thrown back a little, and because of the angle at which he was
sitting, his spectacles caught the light and presented to Winston two black discs
instead of eyes.
What was slightly horrible was that from the stream of sound that poured out of
his mouth, it was almost impossible to distinguish a single word.
Just once Winston quarter phrase—' —'complete and final elimination of
Goldsteinism'— '—jerked out very rapidly and, as it seemed, all in one piece, like a
line of type cast solid.
For the rest it was just a noise, a quack quack quacking
And yet, though you could not actually hear what the man was saying, you could
not be in any doubt about its general nature.
He might be denouncing Goldstein and a demanding sterner measures against
thought criminals and saboteurs, he might be fulminating against the atrocities of
the Eurasian army, he might be praising Big Brother or the heroes on the Malabar
front— —it made no difference.
Whatever it was, you could be certain that every word of it was pure orthodoxy, pure insock
As he watched the eyeless face with the jaw moving rapidly up and down, Winston
had a curious feeling that this was not a real human being but some kind of dummy.
It was not the man's brain that was speaking, it was his larynx.
The stuff that was coming out of him consisted of words, but it was not speech
in the true sense: it was a noise uttered in unconsciousness, like the quacking of a duck
Simon had fallen silent for a moment, and with the handle if his spoon was tracing
patterns in the puddle of stew.
The voice from the other table quacked rapidly on, easily audible in spite of
the surrounding din.
'There is a word in Newspeak,' said Sim I don't know whether you know it
duck speak to quack like a duck.
It is one of those interesting words that have two contradictory meanings.
Applied to an opponent, it is abuse; applied to someone you agree with, it is praise.'
Unquestionably sign will be vaporized, Winston thought again.
He thought it with a kind of sadness, although well knowing that Simon
despised him and slightly disliked him, and was fully capable of denouncing him
as a thought criminal if he saw any reason for doing so.
There was something subtly wrong with Sim There was something that he lacked:
discretion, aloofness, a sort of saving stupidity.
You could not say that he was unorthodox.
He believed in the principles of exoc he venerated Big Brother, he rejoiced over
victories, he hated heretics, not merely with sincerity but with a sort of
restless zeal, an up-to-dateness of information, which the ordinary Party
member did not approach. Yet a faint air of disreputability always clung to him.
He said things that would have been better unsaid, he had read too many books,
he frequented the Chestnut Tree Cafe haunt of painters and musicians.
There was no law, not even an unwritten law, against frequenting the Chestnut
Tree Cafe yet the place was somehow illumined The old, discredited leaders of
the Party had been used to gather there before they were finally purged.
Goldstein himself, it was said, had sometimes been seen there, years and decades ago
Sam's fate was not difficult to foresee.
And yet it was a fact that if Simon grasped, even for three seconds, the
nature of his, Winston's, secret opinions, he would betray him instantly to the Thought Police.
So would anybody else, for that matter: but sign more than most.
Zeal was not enough. Orthodoxy was unconsciousness Sim looked up. 'Here comes Parsons,' he said.
Something in the tone of his voice seemed to add, 'that bloody fool.'
Parsons, Winston's fellow tenant at Victory Mansions, was in fact threading
his way across the room— —a tubby, middle-sized man with fair hair and a frog-like face.
At 35 he was already putting on rolls of fat at neck and waistline, but his
movements were brisk and boyish.
His whole appearance was that of a little boy grown large, so much so that
although he was wearing the regulation overalls, it was almost impossible not to
think of him as being dressed in the blue shorts gray shirt and rednecker chief of the Spies.
In visualizing him one always saw a picture of dimpled knees and sleeves
rolled back from pudgy forearms.
Parsons did, indeed, invariably revert to shorts when a community hike or any
other physical activity gave him an excuse for doing so.
He greeted them both with a cheery hello hello and sat down at the table, giving
off an intense smell of sweat.
Beads of moisture stood out all over his pink face. His powers of sweating were extraordinary.
At the Community center you could always tell when he had been playing table
tennis by the dampness of the bat handle.
Syme had produced a strip of paper on which there was a long column of words,
and was studying it with an ink pencil between his fingers.
'Look at him working away in the lunch hour,' said Parsons, nudging Winston Keen to say
What's that you've got there, old boy?
Something a bit too brainy for me, I expect.
Smith, old boy, I'll tell you why I'm chasing you. It's that sub you forgot to give me.'
'Which sub is that?' said Winston, automatically feeling for money.
About a quarter of one's salary had to be earmarked for voluntary subscriptions,
which were so numerous that it was difficult to keep track of them.
'For Hate Week. You know— —the house by house fund. I'm treasurer for our block.
We're making an all-out effort— —going to put on a tremendous show. I tell you, it
won't be my fault if old Victory Mansions doesn't have the biggest outfit
of flags in the whole street.
Two dollars you promised me.'
Winston found and handed over two creased and filthy notes, which Parsons
entered in a small notebook, in the neat handwriting of the illiterate.
'By the way, old boy,' he said. 'I hear that little beggar of mine let fly at you
with his catapult yesterday.
I gave him a good dressing down for it.
In fact I told him I'd take the catapult away if he does it again.'
'I think he was a little upset at not going to the execution,' said Winston.
'Ah, well— —what I mean to say that shows the right spirit, doesn't it?
Mischievous little big as they are, both of them, but talk about keenness!
All they think about is the Spies, and the war, of course
do you know what that little girl of mine did last Saturday, when her troop
was on a high card birkhamsted way?
She got two other girls to go with her, slipped off from the hike and spent the
whole afternoon following a strange man.
They kept on his tail for two hours, right through the woods, and then, when
they got into amisham handed him over to the patrols.'
'What did they do that for?' said Winston, somewhat taken aback.
Parsons went on triumphantly: 'My kid made sure he was some kind of
enemy agent— —might have been dropped by parachute, for instance. But here's the point oh boy.
What do you think put her on to him in the first place?
She spotted he was wearing a funny kind of shoes— —said she'd never seen anyone
wearing shoes like that before.
So the chances were he was a foreigner.
Pretty smart for a nipper of seven, eh?'
'What happened to the man?' said Winston oh that I couldn't say, of course. But I
wouldn't be altogether surprised if———' Parsons made the motion of aiming a
rifle, and clicked his tongue for the explosion.
'Good,' said Sam abstractedly, without looking up from his strip of paper.
'Of course we can't afford to take chances,' agreed Winston dutifully.
'What I mean to say, there is a war on,' said Parsons.
As though in confirmation of this, a trumpet call floated from the telescreen
just above their heads.
However, it was not the proclamation of a military victory this time, but merely an
announcement from the Ministry of Plenty.
'Comrades!' cried an eager youthful voice.
'Attention, comrades! We have glorious news for you. We have won the battle for
production! Returns now completed of the output of all classes of consumption
goods show that the standard of living has risen by no less than 20 percent
over the past year.
All over Oceania this morning there were irrepressible spontaneous demonstrations
when workers marched out of factories and offices and paraded through the
streets with banners voicing their gratitude to Big Brother for the new,
happy life which his wise leadership has bestowed upon us.
Here are some of the completed figures.
Foodstuffs— The phrase 'our new, happy life' recurred several times. It had been a favorite of
late with the Ministry of Plenty.
Parsons, his attention caught by the trumpets call, sat listening with a sort
of gaping solemnity, a sort of edified boredom.
He could not follow the figures, but he was aware that they were in some way a
cause for satisfaction.
He had lugged out a huge and filthy pipe which was already half full of charred tobacco.
With the tobacco ration at 100 grams a week it was seldom possible to fill a
pipe to the top.
Winston was smoking a Victory Cigarette which he held carefully horizontal.
The new ration did not start till tomorrow and he had only four cigarettes left.
For the moment he had shut his ears to the remoter noises and was listening to
the stuff that streamed out of the telescreen.
It appeared that there had even been demonstrations to thank Big Brother for
raising the chocolate ration to 20 grams a week.
And only yesterday, he reflected, it had been announced that the ration was to be
reduced to 20 grams a week.
Was it possible that they could swallow that, after only 24 hours?
Yes, they swallowed it. Parsons swallowed it easily, with the stupidity of an animal.
The eyeless creature at the other table swallowed it fanatically, passionately,
with a furious desire to track down, denounce and vaporize anyone who should
suggest that last week the ration had been 30 grams slime too— —in some more complex way,
involving double think Sam swallowed it.
Was he, then, alone in the possession of a memory?
The fabulous statistics continued to pour out of the telescreen. As compared
with last year there was more food, more clothes, more houses, more furniture, more
cooking pots more fuel, more ships, more helicopters, more books, more babies— —more
of everything except disease, crime and insanity.
Year by year and minute by minute, everybody and everything was whizzing rapidly upwards.
As Simon had done earlier. Winston had taken up his spoon and was dabbling in
the pale colored gravy that dribbled across the table, drawing a long streak
of it out into a pattern.
He meditated resentfully on the physical texture of life.
Had it always been like this? Had food always tasted like this?
He looked around the canteen.
A low ceiling crowded room, its walls grimy from the contact of innumerable
bodies; battered metal tables and chairs, placed so close together that you sat
with elbows touching Ben spoons, dented trays, coarse white
mugs; all surfaces greasy, grime in every crack; and a sourish, composite smell of
bad gin and bad coffee in the metallic stew and dirty clothes.
Always in your stomach and in your skin there was a sort of protest,
a feeling that you had been cheated of something that you had a right to.
It was true that he had no memories of anything greatly different.
In any time that he could accurately remember, there had never been quite
enough to eat, one had never had socks or under clothes that were not full of
holes, furniture had always been battered and rickety, rooms underheated, tube
drains crowded, houses falling to pieces red dark colored tear rarity, coffee
filthy tasting cigarettes insufficient— —nothing cheap and plentiful except synthetic gin.
And though, of course, it grew worse as one's body aged, was it not a sign that
this was not the natural order of things, if one's heart sickened at the
discomfort and dirt and scarcity, the interminable winters, the stickiness of
one's socks, the lifts that never worked, the cold water, the gritty soap, the
cigarettes that came to pieces, the food with its strange evil tastes?
Why should one feel it to be intolerable unless one had some kind of ancestral
memory that things had once been different?
He looked around the canteen again.
Nearly everyone was ugly, and would still have been ugly even if dressed otherwise
than in the uniform blue overalls.
On the far side of the room, sitting at a table alone, a small, curiously
beetle-like man was drinking a cup of coffee, his little eyes darting
suspicious glances from side to side.
How easy it was, thought Winston, if you did not look about you, to believe that
the physical type set up by the Party is an ideal— —tall muscular youths and deep bosomed
maidens blonde-haired vital, sunburnt, carefree— existed and even predominated.
Actually, so far as he could judge, the majority of people in Airstrip One were
small, dark and ill-favored It was curious how that beetle-like type
proliferated in the Ministries: little dumpy men, growing start very
early in life, with short legs, swift scuttling movements, and fat inscrutable
faces with very small eyes. It was the type that seemed to flourish best under
the domination of the Party.
The announcement from the Ministry of Plenty ended on another trumpet call and
gave way to tinny music.
Parsons, stirred to vague enthusiasm by the bombardment of figures, took his pipe
out of his mouth.
'The Ministry of Plenty certainly done a good job this year,' he said with a
knowing shake of his head.
'By the way, Smith Oldboy I suppose you haven't got any razor blades you can let me have?'
'Not one,' said Winston. 'I've been using the same blade for six weeks myself
oh well— —just thought I'd ask you, old boy.'
'Sorry,' said Winston.
The quacking voice from the next table, temporarily silenced during the
Ministry's announcement, had started up again, as loud as ever.
For some reason Winston suddenly found himself thinking of Mrs Parsons, with her
wispy hair and the dust in the creases of her face.
Within two years those children would be denouncing her to the Thought Police.
Mrs Parsons would be vaporized sign would be vaporized. Winston would be
vaporized. O'Brien would be vaporized.
Parsons, on the other hand, would never be vaporized. The eyeless creature with the
quacking voice would never be vaporized.
The little beetle-like men who scuttled so nimbly through the Labyrinthian
corridors of Ministries— —they, too, would never be vaporized.
And the girl with dark hair, the girl from the Fiction Department— —she would
never be vaporized either.
It seems to him that he knew instinctively who would survive and who would perish
so just what it was that made for survival, it was not easy to say.
At this moment he was dragged out of his reverie with a violent jerk. The girl at
the next table had turned partly round and was looking at him.
It was the girl with dark hair.
She was looking at him in a side long way, but with curious intensity. The
instant she caught his eye she looked away again.
The sweat started out on Winston's backbone. A horrible pang of terror went
through him. It was gone almost at once, but it left a sort of nagging uneasiness behind.
Why was she watching him?
Why did she keep following him about?
Unfortunately he could not remember whether she had already been at the
table when he arrived, or had come there afterwards.
But yesterday, at any rate, during the Two Minutes Hate, she had sat immediately
behind him when there was no apparent need to do so.
Quite likely her real object had been to listen to him and make sure whether he
was shouting loudly enough.
His earlier thought returned to him: probably she was not actually a member
of the Thought Police, but then it was precisely the amateur spy who was the
greatest danger of all.
He did not know how long she had been looking at him, but perhaps for as much
as five minutes, and it was possible that his features had not been perfectly under control.
It was terribly dangerous to let your thoughts wonder when you're in any
public place or within range of a telescreen.
The smallest thing could give you away.
A nervous tick an unconscious look of anxiety, a habit of muttering to yourself—
anything that carried with it the suggestion of abnormality, of having something to hide.
In any case, to wear an improper expression on your face (to look
incredulous when a victory was announced, for example) was itself a punishable offense
There was even a word for it in Newspeak face crime it was called.
The girl had turned her back on him again. Perhaps after all she was not
really following him about; perhaps it was coincidence that she had sat so
close to him two days running.
His cigarette had gone out, and he laid it carefully on the edge of the table. He
would finish smoking it after work, if he could keep the tobacco in it.
Quite likely the person at the next table was a spy of the Thought Police,
and quite likely he would be in the cellars of the Ministry of Love within
three days, but a cigarette end must not be wasted
Sim had folded up his strip of paper and stowed it away in his pocket. Parsons had
begun talking again.
'Did I ever tell you, old boy,' he said, chuckling around the stem of his pipe,
'about the time when those two nippers of mine set fire to the old Market woman's
skirt because they saw her wrapping up sausages in a poster of bb
Sneaked up behind her and set fire to it with a box of matches. Burned her quite
badly, I believe. Little beggars, eh? But keen as mustard! That's a first-rate
training they give them in the Spies nowadays— —better than in my day, even.
What do you think is the latest thing they've served them out with? Ear
trumpets for listening through keyholes!
My little girl brought one home the other night— —tried it out on our sitting
room door, and reckoned she could hear twice as much as with her ear to the hole.
Of course it's only a toy, mind you. Still, gives them the right idea, eh?'
At this moment the telescreen let out a piercing whistle. It was a signal to return to work.
All three men sprang to their feet to join in the struggle around the lifts,
and the remaining tobacco fell out of Winston's cigarette